# Sai Preetham Dongari

dongarisaipreetham@gmail.com | Ph: (214)-843-0664 | saipreethamdongari.vercel.app/

## Summary

Over 2.5 years of experience as a skilled software engineer with expertise in SDLC, specializing in front-end and back-end development with strong proficiency in JavaScript, React.js, Angular, Node.js, Spring Boot, SQL, Python, Java and AWS. My strengths are complemented by strong problem-solving skills, attention to detail, and a passion for staying updated with the latest technologies and best practices.

#### **Education**

### Masters in Computer Science, Clark University | Worcester, MA | GPA: 3.74

May 2024

Excelled as a Teaching Assistant for three consecutive semesters, providing outstanding mentorship and instructional support

B.Tech. in Information Technology, Sreenidhi Institute of Science & Technology | Hyderabad, INDIA | GPA: 8.0

July 2021

Gold Reward for Missing Child Identification project. [International Innovation Show E-NNOVATE Oct 2021]

### **Experience**

# **Open-Source Contributor**

### **One Community Global**

August 2024 – Present | CA, USA

- Reviewed 100+ frontend and backend pull requests, ensuring code quality and consistency using Angular framework and MongoDB.
- · Developed essential API endpoints, UI components, and features with Express.js, React.js, and Redux, enhancing platform functionality.

# **Teaching Assistant**

**Clark University** 

January 2023 - May 2024 | Worcester, MA

- Facilitated hands-on lab sessions for **200+** students, guided them in selecting research topics, and provided feedback on assignments, enhancing their understanding of **Software Engineering** and **Securing the blockchain**.
- Converted and integrated **10000+** rows of CLARKCOUGARS basketball data (1992-2023) into **SQL**, dynamically fetching real-time data using **React Axios**, resulting in significant cost savings for the university by replacing proprietary software.
- Developed a research management app under Prof. Gio using ReactJS, Java Spring Boot, and MongoDB, streamlining research papers.

#### **Software Engineer**

# **Tata Consultancy Services**

August 2021 - July 2022 | Hyderabad, India

- Developed web components and RESTful web services using technologies like Java Spring boot, Angular framework, MySQL, Sitecore, and JDBC, Hibernate. Troubleshooted and resolved multiple bugs within existing features.
- Implemented Angular services to connect the web application to back-end APIs to POST/GET the data used in the application.
- Worked closely with UI/UX designers to implement responsive designs and ensure consistency with design mock-ups, while collaborating
  with other teams to fix user interface defects.

# **Software Engineer**

# **Urban Rebox IT PVT**

January 2020 - June 2021 | Hyderabad, India

- Developed and maintained a responsive frontend for Urban Rebox IT's waste management app using **Angular Framework**, reducing user complaints and improving engagement for **4000+** users.
- Implemented and maintained backend services using Java Spring Boot, ensuring robust and scalable application architecture for the app.
- Took part in designing and optimizing MySQL databases, writing SQL queries and basic stored procedures for real-time data processing, ensuring seamless data flow and improving system efficiency.

#### Skills

**Technical Skills:** C, Python, SQL, HTML, CSS, Bootstrap, JavaScript, TypeScript, React.js, PHP, Node.js, Express.js, Next js, Vue js, Django, Redux, Angular, NgRx, MongoDB, NoSQL, SQL Database Administration, AWS S3, AWS RDS, Restful API's, JWT, OAuth, Git, Postman, Jest, Project Implementation, SaaS, User Experience (UX), Web Experience, Agile, Jenkins.

**Soft Skills:** Effective Communicator, Team Player, Analytical Thinker, Efficient Time Management, Adaptable, Leadership, Creative, Detail-Oriented, Strong Work Ethic, Conflict Resolution.

# **Projects**

### Chat with PDF | Intelligent Document Interaction Platform

January 2024-May 2024

- Developed and deployed "Chat with PDF" using **React.js**, **Tailwind CSS**, **Node.js**, **Express.js**, **AWS S3**, and **Pinecone**, integrating **OpenAI NLP** models to reduce search time by 50% and increase accuracy by 30%.
- Developed backend APIs with **Node.js** and **Express.js**, integrating **AWS S3** and Pinecone for secure, fast semantic searches, achieving a 30% accuracy increase with custom algorithms and real-time query processing.

# Luxora | E-commerce Platform with Admin Panel and Payment Integration

August 2023-Dec 2023

- Created an e-commerce application with a React JS frontend and an admin dashboard using Express and Node for a seamless shopping.
- Integrated **Redux** Toolkit with Async Thunk and React Router v6 for efficient state management and navigation, established a secure backend server with **MongoDB**, **Java Spring Boot** and deployed on **Vercel** with Stripe for payments and **Nodemailer** for emails.

### DocumentGuard | Blockchain-Based Document Storage System

August 2022-December 2022

- Developed a secure, decentralized document storage system using Blockchain, IPFS, and AES encryption, reducing document tampering risks by 40% and enhancing data accessibility by 35%.
- Implemented SHA-256 hashing and a peer-to-peer network with Socket Programming, improving data retrieval speed by 25%.